[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guest is Michael J fredman
Michael J fredman is the Robert Ean
professor in the computer science
department at Princeton University as
well as the co-founder and CTO of time
scale building a category defining
relational database and Cloud platform
for time series data his work broadly
focuses on distribute systems networking
and security and has led to commercial
products deployed systems reaching
millions of users daily honors include
right here's a big list ACM Grace Murray
Hopper award ACM sigops SMG Weiser award
I think ACM fellow presidential early
career award that sounds like a good one
Sloan fellow and the DARPA cssg member
Mike welcome to software engine and
radio is there anything I missed in that
impressive bio that you'd like to add
thanks for having me Gavin I think it's
academics like to give ourselves
Accolade so there you go very impressive
so we're going to have a chat about what
time series data means in 2024 why time
scale DB is needed and how it integrates
with postresql lastly we'll close off
discussing a full example use case so
Mike let's start with time series data
how would you define it today in
2024 we think of Time series data as any
type of metric event information that
you generally want to collect over time
because it changes this is a type of
workload that often actually has a
pattern that makes it look append mostly
so you're often collecting these either
regular or irregular streams of data
and you actually want to collect it over
time because what's valuable to you for
your business for your product is not
only what's happening now but the
ability to look back on how that
information changes over time and use
that to understand the past and also
predict the future what sort of common
time frames do you see in what we
understand time series dat to be I think
it depends a lot on the application you
know we have users who really care about
what happened in the last 24 hours we
often have users in different domains
for example in the energy space in
Renewables in things like oil and gas
there are often compliance reasons and
historical reasons to understand
seasonality where they store it for
going back 10 years and use that you
know also to understand what you know
seasonal Trends are and how the data
changes over time that actually often
translates to features that you end up
building or that you know we end up
building as part of our database to also
recognize that how you might access
information in the last few minutes few
hours might be very different from how
you want to access data or the derived
rollups you have on that data you know
stretching back months or years and what
particular makes this type of data
difficult to work with you know for
example the volumes we get the the time
spons or yeah I think when we set out to
build time scale we did it really
because of the scale and performance
that this domain needs both and you even
alluded to this both the volume and the
velocity of the data is often different
than you might see in a traditional kind
of e-commerce or transactional
application you often have data arriving
at a very fast rate that because you are
also keeping back this historical data
it's not just you know you don't delete
it after a short period of time so that
transits to large data volumes and at
the same time you want to actually build
operational workloads and by that I mean
you're using this data not to you know
you don't throw all this data in some
data lake or data warehouse you never
look at it again when people are coming
to time scale they're doing so because
they're building operational
applications and by that I mean we
actually have developers who are using
this to build products on top of they're
showing those products typically
customer facing their mission critical
and so they also need a responsiveness
and good performance when they're
contining to build those applications
run the apis show the live dashboards to
their customers as opposed to just
somewhere where you know it sits around
for a while and occasionally do some ad
hoc reporting on top of that so it puts
a lot of Demand on what you technically
need for a database in order to satisfy
you know those requirements and I know
you mentioned Mike there operations so
in my head I presume the intervals of
the data we're working with need to be
consumed processed and available in the
Ops tools systems alling monitoring
whatever it is you're actually using
that data and consuming it for pretty
close to the intervals it's arriving or
are there lags that you can accept how
does that look I think what you can
accept often differs by application I
could say that in time scale's case time
scale actually even reserves
transactional semantics so what that
means is as soon as the data is written
into time scale it's available to
queries and also the transactional
semantics mean that it doesn't create
these confusing views for customers or
for users such that you could see these
partial data you know it still maintains
the atomicity that you might expect from
a traditional transactional database
taking a step back you know if I I could
talk about this for a minute which is an
observation that you know we came to
realize after some time working in this
space traditionally when it comes to
databases what a lot of Engineers think
about are these two workload patterns
people talk about called oltp for online
transaction processing or olap for
online analytical processing and this
often had to do with you know oltp are
these really short and simple queries
they're the things that you know are the
back in to your e-commerce site you have
some type of om or some type of software
you do a small read and write to the
database and then olap were these big
analytical workloads where you kept this
really wide row with lots of columns you
threw it in a data warehouse and
occasionally you came back later and
were able to ask random ad hoc queries
of the data I think what we have seen is
two things one is that we are serving
queries that are analytical nature and
so from that regard some of the aspects
are similar to what people traditionally
thought of olap but the big difference
is we actually serve these operational
settings unlike the traditional use case
where again you threw it in this data
warehouse or data Lake and then only
later did people make ad hoc queries
about that and so one of the ways that
changes is that I think it becomes more
about who's using the database
than this definition of the data shape
and what I mean by that is there were
traditional you had developers who are
building applications databases served
as the backend to the applications that
they're developing you know that are
serving their customers critical
internal use cases Etc or you had data
teams which basically had these you know
managed how data flowed through their
system spent a lot of times with ETL
jobs that is ways to move data from
point A to point B and basically became
the owners of the data and almost an
internal service team that gave access
to other people in their organization or
their company but they didn't really
know what they're doing with that their
job was just to bring it together and
let other people do machine learning
reporting or so on on top of that and
the difference is that in the first case
in the developer case which is where we
see a lot of the exciting time series
use cases and where time scale plays is
that the developer comes in often owning
both sides of it they own the data in
and they own how it's used and so they
often think more deeply and design their
schema design the data structures they
have in the database design even their
queries to really be built around
production let's figure out how this
works not because I'm running a one-off
query but because this query is being
triggered or being accessed every time
time a customer hits one of my
dashboards and so you just see end up
different design decisions made in a
database where you actually want to
build for the case where people want
these production workloads as opposed to
let's just throw it somewhere where it's
cheap and we could later do ad hoc
queries against it thank you that's a
very comprehensive explanation there
where are examples of where time scale
DB shines and time series data I think
it ties into what I just described
before which is people
building products
building customer facing apis building
critical dashboards on top of this data
that they're collecting and let me give
you the counter example when you speak
to different people time series data
actually can mean different things not
because the nature of the data which is
you have some type of information that's
being collected over time that's
changing and you want to look at the
history but more about how important it
is for you as a company and how you use
it one of the big places where the
notion of a Time series emerged in the
last 15 years and where you see some of
the
specialization is in server initially
started in what that people called APM
application performance monitoring and
that became broadened into
observability and you see you know there
are both companies that started with APD
and DIN trce and New Relic and more
recently data dog and you often also see
open source software probably the most
best known as Prometheus and now it's
being standardized in open Telemetry
that is focused at collecting the data
the difference here is the use case of
this is typically an internal one and
it's important that you have
observability but if there's any blips
in your observability architecture it's
not great because you're Flying Blind
but that also doesn't mean that your
customers are offline right and so the
use case there is this vertical solution
where the end user might be the s or the
devops team where what they really care
about is are there dashboards there is
there alerting in place they actually
don't really care about the system
behind it and so if you actually look at
what gets built there it's a bunch of
full stack Solutions where you have an
agent running on an end host it's
collecting data it's being kept in a
storage there has been a lot of
innovation on how to make that super
cheap the latest being is to offload it
quickly to an object store like S3 and
then let's actually make it easy to
build dashboards and build a whole
alerting on top of that and so when some
people think about time series data they
immediately go to the observability use
case particularly if they're an engine
engineer who deals at all with
operations but actually we see this and
I explain this by starting with
something that we're not in that you
know we saw this use case of throw your
data somewhere build some dashboards on
this metric not as Mission critical no
need for as much flexibility and no need
to often integrate this with other
important business data as a very
different use case than what time scale
started at and continues to see so when
time skill actually started going back
in history a little bit we were
initially building an iot platform we
wanted a place to collect and store data
coming off the emergence of all these
new types of connected devices and when
we initially attempted to use one of
these time series databases that
actually started also in this
observability space I just saw we kind
of struggled for several different
reasons we struggled because it in
general wasn't performant enough for the
type of workloads we saw and it didn't
focus on the reliability the same way
that we needed and that was iot well we
were starting an iot but we were
initially using a database that had its
roots in this observability space so
just to go back to an example of where
this shines so you're in the historic
part you're in the iot sector yep you're
getting let's call it Telemetry data
from these iot devices the backend
service or database that you've got at
that time is not good enough for what
you're trying to do how does that
present itself to you so you can say
this isn't good enough is that you can't
do certain queries or it's too slow or
you tweaked it to death and you can't
get anything out of it mean what Line in
the Sand you go right this is The Right
Use case for time series data this is
what we're using it's not good enough
let's go build something you know yeah
why did we take the crazy path to go
build a database which seems like a high
bar yeah the two bits to that let's
build a product but also we know this is
the type of data we want to this is how
to model it you know that's why I'm
trying to get to in this section is from
a developer's point of view the question
I'm asking and the answer I'm trying to
get is time series data so I need to
reach for that system right so there are
probably four axes that we saw current
limitations and the first two which I
alluded to already maybe developers can
understand that it was it was really
around the axis of performance and
reliability but the other two I think
were perhaps more instructive even from
day one and that was we really wanted to
use full SQL and we did that because it
has this massive amount of flexibility
and it comes with an entire ecosystem
and if you look at a lot of the
databases that were initially developed
in the space they were squish but you
know they for example didn't allow you
to do joins or include other types of
Clauses in your Clause your aware
predicate which ended up making them a
lot less flexible for the type of
questions you might need and the second
thing was really and I know this sounds
strange is that we wanted or we needed
joins and how that often translates is
not only are you collecting your metrics
the stream of Time series data but you
often have important metadata around it
other types of business data other type
of information that you collected in
this example where this was is we
actually at the time were running two
databases you know one postgress a
traditional relational database and the
other one being this time series
database and we would often want to ask
questions like tell me all devices about
this particular customer that came
online within the last period of time or
all devices of a certain type and this
information is often spread between
these two locations between this
business data and these actually streams
of Time series data now this becomes
very natural in a traditional relational
database and in fact very natural and
ultimately time scale but in a lot of
these things that were built only for
observability or built for metrics you
don't have the ability to do that type
of Rich joins you might expect and so
you end up needing to not just maintain
multiple databases which is
operationally more complex but you
actually need to then in your
application effectively write the
equivalent of a join and not only is
that not as performant but it's more
like hey I want to ask a query and
before I could do the query I actually
need to do a two-e engineering Sprint to
roll it a change to my microservices
that now allow me to do this in
application space and we quickly found
that this would be very not productive
and really went against the type of
platform we actually wanted and so to
solve that iot problem which cared about
operational ease of bringing the data
together so you could do Richard queries
on it which cared about SQL which cared
about performance which cared about
reliability that's actually what
ultimately took us down the path of
building time scale and frankly we think
that those types of requirements are
really fundamental to anybody using time
series in these Mission critical kind of
customer facing settings and we see that
from you know I can talk about it from
iot from product analytics from fintech
we see this in crypto we see it in a lot
of energy sectors we operate in
transportation Logistics backing
e-commerce anything dealing with events
we see that that same requirement to
start an iot really across almost all
application domains yeah I use it myself
time scale DB and obviously with
postrest and a main open source
application I have that consumes voice
over IP fraudulent data so I have all
these different nodes thanks floating
about and they get probes from potential
hackers trying to find open phone
systems and I think the main feature I
use from your product are time buckets
so they can have a heat graph to show
which days had the most events across
the nodes that I run that's good to hear
I actually didn't know that you were
also a user yeah no that's why I reached
out cuz for me as a developer just to go
to summarize what we've just spoken
about in that section and move us on the
web application stack that I use is
Phoenix and elixir so postgress is one
of the main back ends for that and I
knew I needed time series data because
of these events streaming in and I want
to process them and display them all
correctly and time scale DB was just a
really nice fit because I didn't need
anything else I just needed to put in
time scale part and deploy that so yeah
that was just a little example of how I
personally use typ skill DB so I'd like
to take us on to the next section just
to explore why time series data is hard
in traditional databases obviously post
we'll talk about there and why time
scale or how time scale DB makes this
easy so if you when you said that when
you started using post grass did you try
to use that for everything before you
reached for a Time series database from
the beginning we actually started by
splitting our workloads into a Time
series database and you know we kept our
metadata in postr and partly is that we
were concerned from day one about
building for scale and so we kind of
recognized some of the challenges that
traditional relational databases in
postgress and really more the basic data
structures that they use have with
dealing with this type of data and then
of course when he brought them back you
know postris is more than just a
database it's almost a platform for
development and you know we could talk a
little bit about why we're extremely
bullish on postgress and general and why
we've really embraced it in the last de
I'd like to get that in a second CU
we've done a couple of shows on
performance and extending it and
benchmarking it just from a naive
approach yeah if my data is in a
database I would probably do something
like select some of you know the rows
based on a time stamp between midnight
01 and you know 2359 59 across that data
it would be slow because there'll be
lots of rows and there wouldn't be many
indexes on that why is it so much better
with time skill DB or you know a time
series database in general yeah so let
me this is when I'm going to go a little
bit of a deeper dive into maybe data set
some data structures ideas we love that
type of stuff although I'll try to keep
it appropriate level so let's maybe
start with a thought experiment of what
would normally happen if you're writing
to a traditional database and in
particular let's say that you're writing
to a single table and I think that's the
most relevant example you can of course
let's say create a data structure where
you create a table per hour or a
separate table per day that then pushes
off a lot of the management to the
developer where you need to exactly
select which tables per day you want a
query and becomes very hard to write
applications so let's just start by
saying hey we have one table we call it
our metrics and we write everything
there and so if you imagine there's a
couple places where the performance when
you try to query stuff starts to suffer
first of all something like postgress is
traditionally storing their data in what
you'd call row oriented form and so what
that means is that you write a row of
data whether or not it's 50 bytes or 500
or 5,000 bytes row by row as it kind of
comes into the database immediately what
happens if if you turn around and say
hey what happens if I want a query for a
single column over time you actually
need to read the entire row out of the
database in order to access that one
single column and so one part of the way
you query time series databases is you
want to query these scans over a longer
period of time but sometimes for a
smaller number of columns and for those
row oriented databases aren't as
performance for these long types of
scans behind the scenes what time scale
does is the recent data is stored row
colum in row format so we could write to
it really quick because row format is
faster to write because could write row
by row but we actually
change after data reaches a certain age
we actually convert those rows into
compressed columns which allows you to
have much faster scans over time there's
a couple more things but let me talk
about a second main point if you think
about writing to a single table
effectively what you write in is you
write it in the order at which it
arrives at the database so it's get
written to the database in the order
that it gets sent to the database but on
top of that you often as you alluded two
will build indexes one common index
would be based on time the time stamp
that one actually doesn't work that bad
if you think about time as a tree you
might build a traditional B tree over
your data it's kind of right leaning in
that the latest data or leftly depending
on the way you define it but the latest
time stamp is always on one side so if
you query for a recent data all of the
time stamps Associated that data are
kind of in the same region of the tree
of the index structure that actually
will work pretty well because what's
happening under the covers is your
database engine is keeping some of these
index Pages or some of these database
pages in memory the working set and some
of it's on disk so if you are always
interacting with the latest data and if
you look at your index and that is
always part of the same subset of the
index tree that part will actually fit
in memory pretty well and so you'd be
able to make relatively reasonably fast
queries to it on the other hand if you
want other types of indexes which by the
the way are super common for example in
your case you're collecting VoIP data
about your devices and it'd be pretty
common to not only index by time but to
also index by something like device
comma time because during your query you
don't want to just say tell me
information about all my devices it's
pretty common to probably say tell me
information about this specific device
over time by the way do you do that type
of query yeah the probes that come in
are sip so session ini ization protocol
so vo and inside that it'll have a user
agent so that'll be the user agent from
the device it's usually spoofed it might
be a the phone system it's come from
there'll be the phone number that
they're trying to call usually they're
the lowcost ones that they're just
trying to probe to see if they can make
an outside call before premium ones come
through might have a certain prefix we
then look into the IP address to see
what countries they are who allocated
them so there's loads of metadata around
that which you might say sure me all the
user agents that attacked during this
time frame so exactly what you said and
do you index anything other than the
time stamp I think the user agents and
the phone numbers we index by okay and
it also sounds like not every
application is similar in this case it
sounds like you have a highly ephemeral
set of maybe user agents where they
change frequently from a is interesting
but not you know it's not critical yep
but your example it's just one table
called events y totally that is super
common it also makes management a lot
easier but you know going back to the
example I was describing before in this
case if you have an index by let's say
device ID comma timestamp or user agent
comma timestamp the problem is those
user agents are no longer the working
set is spread across all the user agents
in your system and so unlike the time
stamp example where you're always going
to access or the common access patterns
are to like to the portion of the tree
that's the recent
you're probably getting a random set of
device IDs or a random set of user
agents that are being interacted with
and so if you try to build an index over
this first of all you totally can and do
build an index but the access patterns
to this index are somewhat random based
on the device ID or the user agent and
so what that means is that if this
entire index doesn't fit in memory then
you're going to be pulling more and more
data from disk and that is of course
when your performance starts to suffer
because you know memory is a lot faster
than accessing dis and so one of the
things that how this translates to the
way time scale works is that we have the
abstraction which we called hyper tabls
and it looks like a standard table
except under the covers we're actually
doing this really automated partitioning
based on a customer provided
partitioning key which is usually the
timestamp and so what that means is you
basically create a policy that says give
me a new we call it chunks give me a new
chunk or give me a new Partition every
day every week we have some applications
that do it every 10 minutes because
they're really high volume and what that
means is that when you query something
for over time it kind of has additional
metadata so that it doesn't need to
access your data over all time and the
indexes that are built across all time
it only accesses the chunks and only the
small indexes built on them based on
your time interval so if you have three
years of data but you say
you know select star from metrics table
where time stamp is greater than now
minus one day it will only basically run
this query in parallel across the chunks
corresponding to that day and therefore
also use the smaller indexes on top of
them and because the workload patterns
just things are much more likely to be
in memory they're smaller and so that
translates even before we get into all
the fancier stuff like colar compression
that translates to a lot more scalable
and more efficient query
you'll also see as we talk through how
we use the same type of partitioning to
really enact a lot of other policies and
order in our system where you want to
access recent data differently than you
might access old data yeah my uh this
application uses to create hypertable on
the events table on the event timestamp
we have a unique index on the event uu
ID and the event Tim stamp so we don't
get fake data then we have three end X's
which is the source IP of the probe the
number that was attempted to be called
and then the client ID of the for
example the O ID client ID because the
nodes that send in data are all
authorized by an API so they get a
client ID from that so pretty simple and
it's very fast with the bucket window
thing that's what we see a lot we see
people often have these relatively
simple
schemas they're not let's say it's not a
thousand Columns of random data it's
pretty well structured Ed but yeah this
is almost like an audit log table yeah
you've got the application name that's
sending in the probe the version the
time St U ID and then some other
metadata whether it was received by TCP
or UDP you know destination Source IP
the usual things you'd want to see and
then specific things that we want which
is what they're actually trying to do
totally and you know a lot of people
when they think about time series they
often think about this as regular let's
say sensor data that arrives at regular
interval another big use case that it
sounds more similar to what you're doing
are they're really events the
information is used to describe an event
in the system that is irregular nature
and in your case it's these probes these
VoIP or session establishment protocols
when sip runs it's a kind of an event
happening in the system we see the same
thing with product analytics it's when a
user clicks on something in a product or
we see a bunch of people running gaming
applications where it's actually an
in-game event that is being logged to
the database and we actually think of
this as most data at least most high
volume data has that time series nature
to it even if you think about
traditional e-commerce applications
which is like the canonical oltp
application that developers think about
you know where typically is most of your
data where is the biggest table that's
actually your orders table it's a log of
every order placed in the system right
and if you think about it from that
perspective an order is really just an
event log kind of ordered by time and so
that type of event log actually can be
treated and a lot of the technologies
that we built for so-called time series
plays equally with the type of event log
that you have in ntional e-commerce
database so what's interesting is one
thing that we see is that if you start
looking into most databases storing
hundreds of gigabytes terabytes or more
actually where that data is is sitting
in what looks like Time series data and
so it's very applicable to the type of
Technologies we built into post press
it's quite funny because when you come
up the the actual names and Define what
something does you start to see
everywhere don't you say hold on a
minute we can apply that to this and
that and it's just been waiting to be
found we very much agree so just to
close off that section so time scale DB
makes asking these questions and getting
the answers easy because it changes the
column or the row data into columns that
are easy to find and compresses them and
chunks them up is that a dumb way to
express it or yeah there's a couple key
enabling Technologies I already alluded
to one is that we do this automated
chunking or partioning in what we call
hyper tables the second is we as that
data starts to get past its initial
phase where you need High ingest we
change it to a compressed cumar format
which makes quering it both faster as
well as we often see in production 90 95
even 98% compression ratios really
impressive because we've done a lot of
optimized algorithms there we also have
a notion of data life cycle I talked
about from row format to column format
in our Cloud platform for real data we
have tiering to even things like
bottomless storage on S3 and you know
again a different performance cost
trade-off and perhaps the last thing is
we have a technology which we called
continuous aggregate
which if you're a developer coming from
the database space you might call this
an incremental materialized view all
that means it's a fancy word for we
perform automated rollups in the
background so you don't have to do that
so in your example if you're building an
API or building a dashboard we are often
querying the same thing over and over
because it feeds your API or dashboard
you'll basically create that roll up in
the database and whenever data comes in
at a regular inter interval the database
will automatically kind of roll that up
and create that post-processed result
that then gets it's almost like a
caching layer that gets served to the
application but of course unlike caching
you could do full SQL against it and so
that becomes a really powerful way to
again further stress performance for
developers who know the type of
applications they're building fantastic
thank you so now I want to get very
technical and ask you to explain how
time skill DB is integrated with the
famous and all glorious post rescu how
do you do it so we'll see how technical
I actually get but postgress is
interesting in that I allused this
earlier that it's not just a database
but almost becomes a platform and one of
the way that happened is that
almost more than 15 years ago postgress
started down the path of supporting what
is called an extension framework and so
you know what is an extension framework
actually means it means that there's
basically hooks throughout kind of hooks
and callbacks throughout the postgress
software that allows third parties to
come in and write basically you know
integrate themselves such that for
example when a query might come in you
could register a call back to yourself
such that you might get card your
software might get called your extension
software might get called before
standard processing and so there's
somewhat hooked throughout the codebase
so you could decide to integrate
yourself at different points and even in
the last five years there's been even
that framework has been even Rich
through what is called internally in in
postgress software table access methods
and there's even a form of this for
index access methods where you could
build the first part of that integration
was to change the ability to handle SQL
queries and do query processing and now
it makes it easier and EAS easier to not
just handle queries you know DML calls
and schema changes like ddl calls but
also some of the ways you might store
your actual data internally we're
starting to do that with the way we
store our compressed data and some of
the ways you even build indexes the
short answer is what does it mean to
build on top of it it means that you
hook have a bunch of hooks through the
code base you as the developer you know
you continue to write in C it's lowlevel
you're running in the same process space
so you know if you have to be careful
about it because if you have any bugs or
seg faults that of course will you know
crash the whole postest not just your
own little extension and you because
part of it you could actually work on
the same memory space so you have access
to the same memory domains that postest
is normally operating and that allows
you that level of fine grain control the
setup of the application we've been
discussing that I created I've got a
crate extension if not exist time scale
DB so that's a kind of standard post way
to install an extension isn't it
basically there's building extension has
two parts there's obviously the software
that get shipped with the code that you
install and then on top of that on a per
database perspective you have this
command called create extension which is
what in some sense you know loads um the
endpoints from that extension into your
runtime do you get access to all the
native postest utilities like ask for
memory create things you know all the
different hooks so you're not having to
write all this from scratch you get
access to the whole internal post grass
ecosystem of C libraries and functions
you do you you get access to much of it
there are different points in the
postgress codebase that you get
integrated not everybody not everywhere
you know it's it's in general a tradeoff
between what are the things that are
needed as well as you know more hooks
that the core exposes that obviously you
know increases in some sense how much
testing they need to do possibilities
for things going wrong you know I think
one thing that also happened is a lot of
the extensions that are built on
postgress are are relatively simpler or
well constrained they might be things to
let's say support a a certain type they
might extend the functionality to
support a new type of almost like a
built-in UDF a function they might be a
new index type so one of the more
popular ones is post JS which is
geospatial indexing there might be a
bunch of Maintenance things so PG stat
statements is a common extension that
basically keeps track of query execution
time you know something like time scale
you know maybe time scale and another
extension at the time called cus were
probably the first two that really took
it deep that we started changing a lot
more of the internals of
postgress than perhaps was even imagined
when the extension framework was first
built so that you know run into a lot of
pros and cons around that yeah yes so
when you're hooking into these cacks and
hooks for a normal insert that data is
there in a normal database as well but
it has all the time scale bit around it
yeah so it has the time skill but it's
also basically like whenever you query
database that has postest installed and
running effect L we get a call back that
our the code the time scale code there's
a a chain of these call back functions
and we get a callback command that
basically almost is like a handler do
you want to handle that and so we look
at what tables what database objects
that query is touching and if it's
actually affecting one of the hyper taes
or one of the other things under kind of
our management then we will process it
via those rules if not it kind of falls
through and and goes to normal normal
processing it's also the case that we
kind of interact at at different levels
you know we have some code that runs
let's say on your insert pipeline one of
the reasons why if you do an insert we
need to route your insert to the right
chunk that I described before part of
that is also one of the ways that we do
is automated chunk management so if you
are if a chunk is let's say defined for
this 1H hour interval
and the hour threshold passed and you do
a right to that new time stamp which
actually does not have a table to find
on it rather than fail which would occur
if you're doing automated if you're
manually creating these types of
postgress partitions we actually as part
of the insert pipeline will
automatically create this database
object and then insert that data in it
so you again so it's very easier our
code bits are different of course for
the insert pipeline for you know the
query pipelines for you know various
schema modifications and you know it
really it affects many different parts
of the database and you spoke about
rooting it because the data has been
chunked is that something that's
automated based on the type of queries
you're making or is that some type of
configuration thing you need to do as
soon as you ran that create hypertable
command basically everything happens
somewhat automagically for you so that
create hypertable command takes in a in
some sense an interval there is a
default but there's a but that defines
the size of this chunk you could change
it over time and you just write you
could do any type of insert and it will
route that the rows of that insert into
the right chunk it will in many cases
it's the latest in some cases you're
collecting older data so it actually
what we might call back fills to older
time intervals behind the scenes now
that we have this compressed columnar
format transparently handles writing
this data to an uncompressed region next
to the compressed region and then
asynchronously combining the two to
recompress it all that kind of happens
transparently to you as a developer
similarly on the query side in your case
you're just quering that one table of
events you're not realizing that the
query engine under the covers the query
Optimizer is saying okay I have a
thousand tables here based on what the
predicate is I only need to access these
eight chunks of a thousand I'm going to
then in parallel some of these chunks
are compressed some are not I'm going to
actually in parallel execute against
these eight chunks compute any ordering
limiting whatever you want on top of
that and return to the return to the
client all of that is transparent to you
as a developer and it just sits in the
normal sort of storage engine
possibilities that post Crest can offer
yeah we reuse the Heap store in
postgress in a very particular way to
also support our compressed columnar
storage I could kind of go deeper into
that if you want as well as operating
with normal memory spaces as you would
in traditional posts the one place where
that's different is we introduced about
a year ago on our Cloud tiered storage
where beyond having this you know row
based for the very the most recent stuff
compressed storage for most of the hot
stuff this tiered storage which is
basically backed by
S3 tables is for much older data that is
using a kind of a very different
technology than traditional postrest
Heap storage because we're actually
storing these as parquet files on
something like S3 and then building a
query engine on top of that but again
from you as a developer you just quer
your database you transparently decides
do I need to pull this from which type
of storage based on what that you know
wear predicate is you know is this data
in the last month which is all in fast
Year all fast or from five years ago I
need to go back to that tiered storage
back on S3 that's all the Machinery
there though is all transparent to you
as a user and how do you test between
different versions of postgress with
your integration do is there like a a
postgress test weite that you normally
do from the front end with your selects
and things or you have your own custom
test Suites that you used behind the
scenes you know in front of the callbox
or behind the callbox as it were so I
mean testing becomes a whole different
problem or not problem but challenge we
certainly have you know from day one
like many good software engineering
practices we have a full Suite of unit
tests that gets written out on every PR
we use various forms of static analysis
again because we're writing most of this
in in C although we do have some newer
extensions in Rust as well you know
obviously C introduces a lot of that's
what I was going to ask if if that was
around when you're thinking about doing
this rust it wasn't really popular when
we started and also it works well for
some things and it doesn't work as well
for other things part of it is because
we're integrating really closely with
the postgress core that when we do so we
find in many cases that c remains more
appropriately for interacting with it
but to go back to your question we
obviously have a full suit of unit tests
we have static analysis that we run
constantly and we have of course
benchmarking Suites not only for
correctness but also to look at
performance regressions and so we've
been similarly doing a lot of work over
the last year or two around career
performance not just in optimizations we
even I talked about columnar columnar
format we launched last year uh support
for vectorized instruction sets so this
is when you could actually use low-level
instructions in the architecture like
x86 simd instructions and so that
further improves performance so a lot of
what we're also testing for is not just
correctness but also performance
regressions the other thing I will say
is because we write a database but we
also run a cloud with uh thousands of
customers we actually then have a whole
roll out procedure in that we first run
to Dev we first roll out to Dev we roll
out to a first set of services running
on cloud that actually runs time scale
services so we you know we dog food we
build a lot of advanced softwares for
time scale Cloud using time scale
Services the same as our customers and
so we will roll out changes to those
regions we will you know kind of have a
canary approach to roll outs where we'll
roll out new versions to only a
percentage of our customers across
different regions observe how that roll
out might affect performance before and
after because we have a lot of low-level
observability that we could collect
about performance and then use those to
decide to go forward so in some sense we
could build better software because
we're also The Operators of a popular
Cloud today it's the best way isn't it
and do you work closely with a postgress
team when you find things cuz you're in
it so deep so there's two answers first
of all is we've actually for a couple
years employed time scalers who act
actually whose job it is to be Upstream
contributors so one of the things that
was really exciting last year is that we
were you know we're a not the oldest
startup we were in still a relatively
modest sized company we were in the top
10 companies that contributed to
postgress in terms of you know I think
it goes postgress 16 in terms of the
number of contributions or PR reviews or
whatever so we definitely are trying to
work with the community both inside the
core as well as you know building both
the open source extensions as well as
you know our core time SCB which is free
for anybody in the community to use the
good thing is we found that postgress
itself is you know generally very stable
I think they take really the right
approach here is that their goal is
not rapid change but careful Evolution
and I think that has for such a core
piece of technology that has you know
serves almost the whole internet so well
that's really the right approach and so
there have been some ways that we've
contributed Upstream contributed ideas
but the good thing is that the you know
postgress really provides a lot of those
types of hooks that that we use and
other people use to build the type of
extensions I would say that we do have a
lot of experience building a lot more
advanced extensions than most and we've
contributed some ideas around that one
of the areas is that we open sourced
last year a security Checker which we
call PG spot we actually found out that
a vast number of the of postrest
extensions have uh security flaws in
similar manners and so we're actually
just in the in the process of doing a
lot of Outreach to some of these more
another wave of extensions where we
found more flaws and so I don't want to
go into the details yet obvious we'll
put on the show notes and get a link for
people to have a look at them yeah for
responsible disclosure reasons but I
mean there's different ways that people
also contribute to the community and
this is you know our ability to make a
lot of the whole ecosystem more secure
is certainly something that we take a
lot of proud in yeah it's very
impressive thank you so I've got two
questions left before we move on to
discussing a complete example of where
we use time scale DB to finish off the
episode so what makes you the same as
other time series databases so this is a
great question that came from one of the
other volunteer hosts of the show
normally ask which I will ask what makes
you different from everyone else let's
start with what makes you the same as
other time series da basis I think one
of the ways that we're the same is we
often try
to look at the same type of workloads
and in many databases they have the
notion of you know if you pull
a common use case for postest including
with an OM they often talk about a crud
workload create read delete or update
delete and that often by its nature is
very key value store it's Point queries
it's create a row update a row read a
row delete a row because you're managing
them like a user table and I think the
workload for somebody dealing with time
series or events internally we sometimes
refer to this as it's an acronym we
don't used publicly too much but I
really like it is awesome append update
scan materialize by that I mean you're
not creating a random record you're
append most records are being appended
to the end of your database occasionally
due to updates but they're not as
primary use case scan you are often not
reading an individual row you are
looking at data over a larger period of
time and materialize it's not all about
these random scans it's that you often
have no things that you want to access
so it is beneficial to you to
materialize those results so you could
satisfy those common queries quickly and
so I think if you look at a number of
the databases that try to handle this
data even though they might say it they
optimize for these things like insert
heavy or append heavy as I described
they optimize for these scans over
longer periods of time they may have
some support for materialization to
enable fast queries to known things you
want so I think you often seem those at
least goals of similarities I think to
be honest the biggest difference is that
most teams that have gone down this path
thought they needed to build something
from scratch and perhaps the biggest way
that time skill is different and then
building something from scratch comes
with a lot of trade-offs uh not just in
terms of the
flexibility and the richness of both the
query language the database
functionality but I think it that
ecosystem takes a long time to develop
both for the features inside the
database as well as the software built
around it that you could use you
mentioned earlier that hey you went to
get elixir it just worked with with time
scale it worked with time scale not
because of what we did it worked with
time scale because it works with
postgress and the last thing is people
is the ecosystem is the developers who
know how to use it and it could be come
efficient really quickly and they they
have a mental model of what's Happening
they understand kind of more implicitly
what it probably could do or what it
can't do and so there's not that whole
learning phase that normally accompanies
this brand new technology so I think
that's probably the biggest changes is
our ability to build this on top of
postrest that's great you've covered
both of my questions here what makes you
the same and different and that was the
one of the biggest surprising things for
me is I imagined in my head when I read
the articles and you know came across
the name the different blog post I was
reading that would be like this time
scale. DB file like SQL light or
something in my application and it was a
real pleasant surprise when I saw it was
part of postc Crash that way yeah that's
actually the common when I think about
our customer Journey or our user Journey
the very common user Journey that we
have is that a developer starts building
their application and they immediately
reach to postgress because in some sense
that's become the default today it's the
no-brainer I don't know what I want to
do I reached a post is this great
flexible powerful thing that's not going
to fail me and at some point what
happens is their product takes off they
start inserting more data they're
starting to encounter these problems and
so you know we kind of think that what
we've done is we've made postgress
powerful we've scaled the performance of
postgress to make it work for these
demanding applications like in iot
sensor data crypto AI events
where you know in general time series
data and others where you need you you
love the ecosystem and reliability and
everything that you understand about
postgress but you need it to scale more
you need more performance you need more
features for this type of use case and
so your two options are either really
abandoning postgress and going to some
more Niche database that has of course
other problems and unknown unknowns or
try to figure out how you can continue
to scale with postgress and I think
that's really where the part of a
journey that we come in that we've
enabled people to scale with postgress
and people are often surprised on how
far you could actually scale it I talked
earlier about in running our Cloud we
build our actually own services on top
of time scale and what's really
interesting is the way we do that now is
we actually use in our Cloud you know we
have vanilla time skill services like
any customer does and the thing that
actually is backing our production
some of the production features we have
our you know our vanilla time skill
services that is we build on top of the
same thing that all of our customers can
use one example of this is we have a new
insights product features that basically
gives you really lowlevel information
about how your queries are working so it
collects sketches of every database
query that you do properly nor
normalized it covers the the shape of
queries timing information how many
pages it hit in memory you know lock
disciplines it allows you really to
drill into individual queries to
understand actually how your database is
operating and where things are working
fast and where things might be working
slow and how to debug it why do I bring
this up that service which is a standard
time skill service ingests about 10
billion records a day and is approaching
a petabyte so normally you don't think
of it's using tiered storage it's using
colar compression all this stuff
normally you don't think of a poststress
database as being a petabyte that's what
we actually and that is customer facing
it serves all of our customers and so
indeed you can actually make postgress
scale well that's looped back nicely to
the start of the show when I was looking
for some scalability numbers so it's a
great way to help us finish up the show
on an example so what I'd like to close
off with is an example project could be
anything time series related obviously
that covers how we set up time scale DB
how we scale it important things that a
lot of people don't talk about is the
operational side you know how do we back
it up how do we check that it's working
okay um how do we upgrade it which is
that just upgrading post grass or is
that something else so we've got around
10 15 minutes for that you like to have
a stab mik so let's start how do we get
set up with a vanilla time scale DB I
have two answers here one is that
there's the how you do all these things
if you're using time scales you know
open source or free version of time
scale and there's obviously how you do
that if you use time scale Cloud which
is you know wildly easier than the
former so let me somewhat answer this in
two ways of course the easiest is or
many of these instructions are in our
docs so any listener is certainly
welcome to log into our doc or to go to
our docs and just to follow the various
instructions to you know be able to copy
and paste various commands the good
thing is if you're
if the listeners are familiar with how
to manage postrest managing time scale
looks incredibly similar and you know
that's because for the most part time
scale somewhat innovates on the
internals of the database how we might
store data how we might query data what
SQL features we support not actually on
the operation side you mentioned already
the one additional things about
installation again this only applies if
you're self-managing the software not
using our Cloud where you don't need to
worry about any of this but not only do
you install postgress but you also
install the time scale binaries the
other thing I would add is if you go to
again our docs we have Docker images and
other build commands that and other RPMs
and other Ubuntu images and whatnot that
will make it very easy to install this
using you know standard package managing
software but once you install time WB if
you're running self-managed inside your
database you just run this one command
create extension that's a standard
command in postgress for extension
management and that kind of enables it
for your application yeah that's what I
do I pull in the time scale DB Docker
image in my development environment and
then run that create extension yep when
it comes to some operational things like
ha High availability replicas either
running replicas purely for for failover
or for scaling re queries again that
looks very much like traditional
postgress operations you set up uh
streaming replication between a primary
and a replica the same way that you
would with postgress if you're again
self-managing the built-in open source
postgress will enable you to stream to a
replica it won't provide this broader
framework to detect when a primary mic
goes down and then execute the command
man to fail over to the replica that's
often done with other open source
software one of the common ones is
called Patron that's a very common in
the postrest community for managing this
type of of Open Source or to manage this
type of failover that works very
naturally also if you're running time
scale in fact two of the initial three
Engineers who developed Pon time were at
a company called zolando actually now
have been at time scope for the last
four or five years so it's also
technology that we use heavily
internally as well when it comes to
backup you could run traditional backups
whether or not they're you know whole
backups like PG dump PG restore or as
well as streaming incremental backups
that allow Point time recovery one
common one might be PG back rest we also
use that internally there's other ones
like wall G those all similarly work
with time scale so the good thing is if
you're deciding to self-manage time
scale many of the operations that you
have for postgress
also work with time scale maybe a better
way to ask this section is what tools
wouldn't you use thought you would
normally use for postc I would say two
of the ways that are different is that
number one upgrades are slightly
different and that is because you
upgrade postgress and you upgrade the
extensions on postgress separately that
makes sense because when we we might
release software we release software
obviously as a different Cadence than
postgress does so there is a standard
postgress command for updating extension
and that of course runs with time scale
but I think that where some care needs
to be taken is version compatibility in
that we typically build our extension to
be compatible to the last it's always
been to three major versions of postest
sometimes four major versions of
postrest but you know sometimes
especially when people are self-managing
upgrades can be harder so they don't do
them for many years and so occasionally
we find you know customers who might
still be running let's say pg11 and an
old version of time scale they want to
upgrade to the latest version of time
scale the latest version of time scale
might only run I think it's I forget if
latest version is pg12 or PG-13 onward
and so they actually have to in some
sense upgrade these in in kind of a
couple different stages where they might
upgrade to one version of time scale
upgrade postgress the latest then
upgrade time skill again to latest
version that fits in the latest version
of postrest so there's a little bit of a
compatibility Matrix that people need to
think about of course keep your upgrades
up to date so you don't need to worry
about this or if you use the cloud we
make sure that all these updates are
always kept up to date so you don't need
to worry about this either the last
thing I would say is databases are
generally easy to operate when they're
small they get harder to operate when
they're big or more things could go
wrong you know we're very used to
running production databases at terabyte
and multi-terabyte scale we have a lot a
lot of customers who do that in
production our experience is some of the
places where people get into trouble
when they're self-managing is it seems
really easy to get a database running
when it's 10 gigabytes but then trying
to manage you know reliable replicas
reliable incremental backups you know
actually running doing smoke testing on
your backups making sure all that you
could spin these up make sure you do
upgrade smoothly that becomes hard to do
in a self-managed environment when
you're running at scale starting you
know hundreds of gigabytes certainly
terabytes thousands hundreds of
thousands of database objects and so
that's just something for people to be
conscious of and considered of is to
make sure you have great dbas when you
start getting into that scale or of
course you know look to manage service
yeah I've been caught out with a just in
the dev environment upgradeing between
Docker images because they come as one
thing normally the image has got the
latest version tied to that postgress
version so I got in a little bit of a
mess but it's just cuz I didn't read the
docs
properly okay that's great it's obvious
it was a great choice to have postgress
as the core and hook into that because
it comes with so much more that you
didn't need to invent yourself then just
itate on which is brilliant you've
explained about how the cloud stuff
works as well to make our lives easier
which is great I think I'm going to wrap
up the show now if that's okay I think
we've done a great job of covering what
time series data is and what time scale
DB brings but a question I like to
always ask at the end of my show if
there was one thing that you'd like a
software engineer to remember from this
episode what would you like it to be
Mike I think postgress is for everything
and so we really believe that Engineers
could make their jobs simpler more
reliable and more flexible if rather if
trying to simplify their stack by
putting you know 99% of workloads
probably will work with postgress and
the things that have made it powerful
like time scale like the things we've
done for time series Ai and whatever as
opposed to build this very Rube Goldberg
like ecosystem of lots of databases lots
of Integrations lots of etls and so we
think that you know Simplicity can be
king and developers can go a lot farther
than they ever thought possible with
just postgress thank you was there
anything we missed in the show that you
thought might come up or you'd like to
mention I think that's uh great Gavin I
mean if anybody wants to check it out of
course they could look at you know times
skill.com both see about our database
software itself as well as the cloud
experience we built and you know our
what what makes us excited every day I
think is that we have users who are you
know building in many cases the future
of computing and you know anywhere from
you next Generation energy to satellites
and space to Fusion Technologies to new
forms of finance and and
monetary forms it's really an exciting
time to be working on data
infrastructure and to enable developers
to be kind of the creative people that
they are and where can people connect
with you if they want to follow up or
have any questions about things that
were mentioned easiest way maybe is even
on Twitter at Michael fredman or I am
Mike at timescale if he is interested
excellent I'll put those in the show
notes Mike thank you for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure this is
Gavin Henry for software engineering
radio thank you for listening thank you
for having
me thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com
you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening